A Guide to the Historical Portraits Collection, 1679-1893
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Historical Portraits Collection 1679-1893
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10213, -a, -b, -d, -e, -f
ca. 95 engraved and lithographed portraits
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased in installments between 1977 and 1982 from Colburn & Tegg, Hollis, N.Y.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 95 engraved and lithographed portraits. The subjects of the portraits are: Jeffrey Amherst, Sir Edmund Andros, Henry Bennet, earl of Arlington, Charlotte (Consort of George III), William Clark, Henry Clay, William Harris Crawford, Elizabeth Moss Crittenden, James Currie, Edward Sackville Dorset, Henry Draper, Myra Clark Whitney Gaines, Edward J. Gay, George I, George III, George, Prince of Denmark, Alfred Griffith, Samuel Hammond, William Henry Harrison, Patrick Henry, John Hunter, Andrew Jackson, Stonewall Jackson, James, I, Elisha Kent Kane, Henry Lee, Robert E. Lee, Sir Thomas Lunsford, Dolley Madison, James Madison, John Marshall, James Monroe, Cyrus Hall McCormick, John W. Nash, Pocahontas and John Smith, Edgar Allan Poe, Sydenham Poyntz, Sir Walter Raleigh, William H. Richardson, Robert, earl of Warwick, Winfield Scott, Thomas Shirley, Sir Thomas Smith, Josiah Tattnall, Zachary Taylor, Julia Gardiner Tyler, Mrs. Robert Tyler, Sir William Wadd, Daniel Webster and William Wirt. The Monroe engraving includes a vignette of Lafayette's U.S. visit.
There is also a portrait entitled "President & Generals C.S.A." that is a composite of portraits of Jefferson Davis, Robert E. Lee, A.P. Hill, J.E.B. Stuart, Braxton Bragg, Joseph E. Johnston, John Morgan, Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson, and P.G.T. Beauregard.
John Hunter and Thomas Shirley are University of Virginia graduates.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by surname of the subject. Multiple portraits of a single subject are subarranged chronologically when possible.
Contents List
- Amherst, Jeffery Amherst, Baron (1717-1797); 1832 (Folder 1)
  "From the original of Sir Joshua Reynolds in the collection of the Right Honble. the Earl Amherst" "London: Published Novr. 1, 1832, by Harding, Lepard, Pall Mall East"
- Amherst, Jeffery Amherst, Baron (1717-1797); n.d. (Folder 2)
  "From the original of Sir Joshua Reynolds in the collection of the Right Honble. the Earl Amherst" "The London Printing and Publishing Company" Same image as folder 1, above, within elaborate ornamental border.
- Amherst, Jeffery Amherst, Baron (1717-1797); n.d. (Folder 3)
  "T. Miller Sc."
- Andros, Edmund, Sir (1637-1714); n.d. (Folder 4)
  "H. Lieblerz, sc."
- Andros, Edmund, Sir (1637-1714); n.d. (Folder 5)
  "Engd. By E.G. Williams & Bro. .N.Y."
- Arlington, Henry Bennet, Earl of (1618-1685); n.d. (Folder 6)
  "The effigies of the Right Honble. Henry Bennet Earle and Baron of Arlington, Viscount Thetford, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, Lord Chamberlaine of his Ma.tys Household and one of the Lords of his most Honourable privy Councell ca."
- Arlington, Henry Bennet, Earl of (1618-1685); n.d. (Folder 7)
  "Lely pinx."
- Arlington, Henry Bennet, Earl of (1618-1685); 1836 (Folder 8)
  "From the original of Sir Peter Lely, in the collection of the Right Honble. Lord De Clifford" "London: Published December 1, 1836, by Harding & Lepard, Pall Mall East"
- Beauregard, P. G. T. (Pierre Gustave Toutant) (1818-1893) (Folder 9)
  See Folder 64 "President & Generals C.S.A."
- Bragg, Braxton (1817-1876) (Folder 10)
- Charlotte, consort of George III, King of Great Britain (1744-1818); n.d. (Folder 11)
  After Gainsborough; engraved by Read.
- Charlotte, consort of George III, King of Great Britain (1744-1818); 1809 (Folder 12)
  "From an original picture by Sir William Beechey, R.A. in his own possession. Drawn and engraved by W. Evans. Published March 1, 1809, by T. Cadell & W. Davies, Strand, London."
- Clark, William (1770-1838); n.d. (Folder 13)
  "The Southern History Co. Eng. by Williams N.Y."
- Clay, Henry (1777-1852); n.d. (Folder 14)
  "On steel [illegible] by John Sartain, Phila." Group portrait of Clay with Andrew Jackson and Daniel Webster.
- Crawford, William Harris (1772-1834); n.d. (Folder 15)
  "Engraved by S.H. Gimber from a portrait by J.W. Jarvis"
- Crittenden, Elizabeth Moss, (b. 1803 or 4); n.d. (Folder 16)
- Currie, James (1756-1805); 1816 (Folder 17)
  "Engraved by W.T. Fry, from a miniature by T. Hargreaves, in the possession of W.W. Currie, Esq. Published Nov. 1, 1816, by T. Cadell & W. Davies, Strand, London."
- Davis, Jefferson (1808-1889) (Folder 18)
- Dorset, Edward Sackville, Earl of (1591-1652); 1836, 2 copies. (Folder 19)
  "Engraved by P. Lightfoot. From the original of Vandyke, in the collection of His Grace the late Duke of Dorset. London: Published Decr. 1, 1836, by Harding & Lepard, Pall Mall East."
- Dorset, Edward Sackville, Earl of (1591-1652); 1836 (Folder 20)
  "Sr. Ant. Van Dyck pinx. M. V dr. Gucht scut." From History of the Rebellion and Civil Wars in England ?
- Dorset, Edward Sackville, Earl of (1591-1652); n.d. (Folder 21)
  "From the original by Van Dyck in the Dorset collection."
- Draper, Henry (1837-1882); n.d. (Folder 22)
  "P. Raymond Audibert"
- Gaines, Myra Clark (1805-1885); n.d. (Folder 23)
  "Engd. By H.B. Hall N.Y."
- Gay, Edward I (b. 1816); n.d. (Folder 24)
  "Bureau. Engraving & Printing"
- George I, King of Great Britain (1660-1727); 1746 (Folder 25)
  "G. Kneller pinxit. Impensis J. & P. Knapton, Londini. J Houbraken sculps. Amst. 1746." "At Kensington Palace"
- George III, King of Great Britain (1738-1820); [ca. 1852] (Folder 26)
  "First meeting of George III and Princess Charlotte of Mecklenburg-Strelitz" Removed from The History of England from the Text of Hume and Smollett, Continued to the Present Time by Thomas Gaspey.
- George, Prince, consort of Anne, Queen of Great Britain (1653-1708); 1745 (Folder 27)
  "G. Kneller pinxit. Impensis J. & P. Knapton, Londini. J Houbraken sculps. Amst. 1745." "At Kensington Palace"
- Griffith, Alfred, Rev. n.d., 2 copies; copy 2 heavily foxed and stained. (Folder 28)
  "Ambrotype by Pollock. Engraved by J.C. Buttre, N.Y. Middleton Strobridge & Co. Prs. Cinti. O." "Engraved expressey [sic] for the Ladies repository"
- Hammond, Samuel (1757-1842); n.d. (Folder 29)
  "Engraved by J.C. Buttre"
- Harrison, William Henry (1773-1841); n.d. (Folder 30)
  "J. Kirk. J.C. Buttre"
- Henry, Patrick (1736-1799); n.d. (Folder 31)
- Henry, Patrick (1736-1799); n.d. (Folder 32)
  "Engraved by E. Wellmore from a painting by J.B. Longacre after an original miniature in possession of John S. Fleming of Virginia"
- Hill, Ambrose Powell (1825-1865) (Folder 33)
- Hunter, John (1866-?); n.d. (Folder 34)
  "Eng. by E.G. Williams & Bro. N.Y. The New York History Co."
- Jackson, Andrew (1767-1845) (Folder 35)
  See Folder 14, Henry Clay
- Jackson, Stonewall (1824-1863); 1874 (Folder 36)
  "Likeness from an authentic photograph from life. Johnson, Wilson & Co. Publishers, New York"
- Jackson, Stonewall (1824-1863); n.d. (Folder 37)
  Within elaborate ornamental border; above vignette with title "Stonewall Jackson mortally wounded"
- Jackson, Stonewall (1824-1863); n.d. (Folder 38)
- James I, King of England (1566-1625); n.d. (Folder 39)
  after Paul Van Somer
- Johnston, Joseph E. (Joseph Eggleston) (1807-1891) (Folder 40)
  See folder 64 "President & Generals C.S.A."
- Kane, Elisha Kent (1820-1857); 1862 (Folder 41)
  "Likeness from the latest photograph from life. Johnson & Fry Co., Publishers, New York."
- Kane, Elisha Kent (1820-1857); 1876 (Folder 42)
  Published by Virtue & Yorston
- Kane, Elisha Kent (1820-1857); n.d. (Folder 43)
  "Dagd. By Brady. T. Phillibrown Sc."
- Lee, Henry (1756-1818) (Folder 44)
  "J. Herring after Stuart. J.F.E. Prud'homme Sc."
- Lee, Henry (1756-1818) (Folder 45)
  "G.R. Hall"
- Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward) (1807-1870); n.d. (Folder 46)
  "Likeness from an approved photograph. Johnson, Wilson & Co. Publishers, New York."
- Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward) (1807-1870); n.d. (Folder 47)
  "Engraved by A. Ròbin"
- Lunsford, Thomas, Sir (1610?-1653?); n.d. (Folder 48)
  "S Harding del. W N Gardiner sculp. From an original portrait in the collection of Richard Aldworth Neville, Esq."
- McCormick, Cyrus Hall (1809-1884); n.d. (Folder 49)
  "Painted by Cabanel. Engd. By A.H. Ritchie"
- Madison, Dolley (1768-1849) n.d. (Folder 50)
  "From an original portrait by Gilbert Stuart in possession of Richard Cutts, Esq. M.D. Washington. New York, D. Appleton & Co."
- Madison, James (1751-1836); [1876?] (Folder 51)
- Madison, James (1751-1836); n.d. (Folder 52)
  "Engd. by H.B. Hall & Sons, New York"
- Madison, James (1751-1836); n.d. (Folder 53)
  within elaborate ornamental frame; above vignette.
- Marshall, John (1755-1835); 1863 (Folder 54)
  "Johnson, Fry & Co. Publishers, New York"
- Marshall, John (1755-1835); n.d. (Folder 55)
  "Painted by Henry Inman. Eng. by A.B. Durand"
- Monroe, James (1758-1831); n.d. (Folder 56)
  within elaborate ornamental frame; above vignette entitled "Public entry of La Fayette into New York"
- Morgan, John Hunt (1825-1864) (Folder 57)
- Nash, John W. (1752-1835); n.d. (Folder 58)
  "R. Thew[?] Sc. Engd. for Biographical Sketches of Eminent Americans "
- Pocahontas (d. 1617); 1793, Aug. 10 (Folder 59)
  "Matoaka als Rebecca filia potentiss. Princ: Powhatani imp: Virginiae," "Matoaks als Rebecka daughter to the might Prince Powhatan Emperour of Attanoughkomouck als virginia converted and baptized in the Christian faith, and wife to the worff. Mr. Joh Rolff. Pubd. Augt. 10. 1793 by W. Richardson Castle St. Leicester Square."
- Pocahontas (d. 1617); 1874 (Folder 60)
  "Pocahontas saving the life of Capt. John Smith. From the original painting by Chappel in the possession of the publishers. Johnson, Wilson & Co. Publishers, New York."
- Pocahontas (d. 1617); n.d. (Folder 61)
  "G. Staal. B. Eyles. Imp. F. Charden aine, 30 r. Hautfeuille, Paris"
- Poe, Edgar Allan (1809-1849) (Folder 62)
  Removed and filed in Barrett Poe.
- Poyntz, Sydenham. n.d. (Folder 63)
  "Engraved from Riecrafts Survey of England's champions. Published by W. Richardson, Castle Street, Leicester Square"
- "President & Generals C.S.A." (Folder 64)
  "Engraved and published by J.C. Buttre, 48 Franklin St. New York"
- Raleigh, Walter, Sir (1552?-1618); 1829 (Folder 65)
  "Engraved by H. Robinson. From the original of Zucchero, in the collection of the Most Noble the Marquis of Bath. London, Published June 1, 1829, by Harding & Lepard, Pall Mall East."
- Raleigh, Walter, Sir (1552?-1618); n.d. (Folder 66)
  "Engraved by J. Posselwhite. From a picture in the collection of the Duchess of Dorset. Under the supervision of the Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge. London, Published by Charles Knight, Ludgate Street."
- Richardson, William H. (1864-1937); n.d. (Folder 67)
  "Ludwig & Keatinge Richmond, Va."
- Scott, Winfield (1786-1866); 1857 (Folder 68)
  "Martin, Johnson & Company, Publishers, New York."
- Scott, Winfield (1786-1866); 1862 (Folder 69)
  "Likeness from a recent photograph from life. Johnson, Fry & Co., Publishers, New York."
- Scott, Winfield (1786-1866); n.d. (Folder 70)
  "Engraved by W.G. Armstrong from a printing by C. Ingham"
- Scott, Winfield (1786-1866); n.d. (Folder 71)
  "Engd. by Chas. Hall from a daguerreotype by Brady." within elaborate ornamental frame; above vignette entitled "Niagara"
- Scott, Winfield (1786-1866); n.d. (Folder 72)
  Same image as folder 71, above, without ornamental frame or vignette.
- Scott, Winfield (1786-1866); n.d. (Folder 73)
  "H.B. Hall. From a recent photograph by Brady"
- Scott, Winfield (1786-1866); n.d. (Folder 74)
  "Engraved by E. Teel. Daguerreotyped by E. Gurney."
- Scott, Winfield (1786-1866); n.d. (Folder 75)
  "Engraved by J.C. Buttre N.Y."
- Shirley, Thomas (1827-?); n.d. (Folder 76)
  "engd. by H.B. Hall & Sons 62 Fulton St. N.Y."
- Smith, John (1580-1631); n.d. (Folder 77)
  "The portraicture of Captayne Iohn Smith, Admirall of New England." "These are the Lines that shew thy Face, but those / That shew thy Grace, brighter bee. / The Faire-Discoueries and Fowle-Overthrowes / Of Salvages, much civiliz'd by thee / Best shew thy Spirit and to it Glory Wyn; / So, thou art Brasse without--but Golde within."
- Smith, Thomas, Sir (1558?-1625); n.d. (Folder 78)
  "Vera effigies praeclariss. mi. viri domni: Thomae Smith eqvitis aurati etc." "The honourable Sr. Thomas Smith Knight, late Embassador from his Mastie to ye great Emperour of Russie Gouernour of ye Honble and famous Societyes of Marchants tradinge to ye East Indies Muscovy the French and Somer Islands Company Tresurer for Virginia, etc."
- Stuart, Jeb (1833-1864) (Folder 79)
- Tattnall, Josiah (1795-1871); n.d. (Folder 80)
- Taylor, Zachary (1784-1850); 1863 (Folder 81)
  "At the period of commanding in Mexico. From the original picture in the possession of the Publishers. Johnson, Fry & Co. Publishers, New York."
- Taylor, Zachary (1784-1850); n.d. (Folder 82)
- Taylor, Zachary (1784-1850); n.d. (Folder 83)
  "Rice & Buttre"
- Taylor, Zachary (1784-1850); n.d. (Folder 84)
  "Engraved by T.H. Welch (Phila.) from a daguerreotype by Maguire. Printed by A.E. Lent & Co."
- Tuley, Mrs. n.d. (Folder 85)
  "Engd. by H.B. Hall, N.Y."
- Tyler, John (1790-1862); [1893?] (Folder 86)
- Tyler, Julia Gardiner (1820-1889); n.d. (Folder 87)
- Tyler, Elizabeth Priscilla (1816-1889); n.d. (Folder 88)
- Wadd, William, Sir; 1798, January 1 (Folder 89)
  "The liuely portraiture of the worthy knight Sir William Wadd late Lieutenant of the Tower, c. Published Jany. 1st 1798, by Wm. Richardson York House No. 31 Strand."
- Warwick, Robert Rich, Earl of (1587-1658); n.d. (Folder 90)
  "The Right Honble. Robert Earle of Warwick Lord Rich of Leeze & Lord High Admiral of the Seas"
- Warwick, Robert Rich, Earl of (1587-1658); n.d. (Folder 91)
  "The Right Honovrable Robert Earl of Warwick, Baron of Leeze, c. Lord High Admiral of England, one of his Majesty's most honourable Privy Council, and his Majesty's Lieutenant of the Counties of Norfolk, Essex, c."
- Webster, Daniel (1782-1852) (Folder 92)
- Wirt, William (1772-1834); n.d. (Folder 93)
  "C.B. King A.B. Walter"